ILGWU Education Department Publications 5780/166 PUBS
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Education Department Publications
1920-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/166 PUBS
3.11 cubic feet
3.1 linear ft.
Publications (documents).
This collection consists of publications either created or collected by the Education Department. Publications include speeches and articles by Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, and reports of the Education Department and the Ladies Apparel Accessories Council.
7128174
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, July 20, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Local union's of the ILGWU established and maintained robust, ambitious educational departments early on in the international's history. As these groups grew in size and scope, the international office sought to coordinate and centralize educational programming for the union's members, culminating in the formation of the Educational Department in 1918.
The department's programming included courses at the Workers' University at the Washington Irving High School in New York City, lectures at Unity Centers and Unity Houses in the northeastern United States, and other events. The educational offerings of the International's Education Department were varied, as had been the education departments of the local unions, and included not only classes in labor studies but also courses in languages, music, and the arts. The ILGWU's 1937 musical "Pins and Needles" exemplified the diversity of the union's programs.
Directors of the Education Department, especially Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, wrote extensively on the ILGWU's programs and worker education in general. Longtime director Gus Tyler not only directed the department, but also served as the ILGWU's on-staff scholar. In later years, the Education Department went beyond collaborating with other education organizations and arranging in-house programs to also supporting post-secondary education for union members and their families.
Scope and Contents
The Education Department records document activities across the entire period of the department's existence, with the bulk of the records covering the 1970s and 1990s. It contains papers from directors of the Education Department: Fannia Cohn, Mark Starr, Gus Tyler, and Kitty Krupat.
The earliest documentation of the department's work is found in the Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049, 5780/049 P); these contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, photographs, and printed material from her work as director of the Educational Department. A microfilm copy of the Fannia Cohn papers held at the New York Public Library (5998 mf) complements the Kheel Center's holdings. Documentation of the work of another longtime leader of the Education Department, Mark Starr, is contained in these records (5780/166, 5780/166 PUBS), as well as in a related collection from Starr on worker education programs (5243).
Documentation of the work of Gus Tyler, who led the merged Education and Political Department after Mark Starr's retirement in 1960, is also contained in the ILGWU records (5780/052, 5780/088, 5780/096). Tyler's papers are complemented by those of Assistant Director Jasper Peyton (5780/086) and Special Projects Coordinator Beverly Shulman (5780/106). These collections contain routine correspondence and memoranda, reports, materials relating to training institutes, seminars, and conferences, and printed material.
The papers of Kitty Krupat, who was serving as Education Director at the time of the ILGWU/ACTWU merger in 1995, constitute the entirety of Education Department records from the 1990s. They include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records relating to the ILGWU's independent and collaborative education projects, including the Worker-Family Education Program, the Joint Union-University Committee on Labor Education, and the Consortium for Worker Education, as well as numerous trainings, conferences, and seminars. Also included in the files are materials from local unions and regional departments of the ILGWU, files on the Internationals' conventions, and reports to the General Executive Board.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/106: ILGWU Education Department, Beverly Shulman Papers 5780/138: ILGWU Education Department, Kitty Krupat Papers 5780/166: ILGWU Education Department Records 5780/086: ILGWU Education Department, Jasper Peyton Papers 5780/049: ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Papers 5780/049 P: ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Photographs
Women's clothing industry--United States.; Clothing workers--Labor unions--United States.; Clothing workers--United States.; Industrial relations--United States.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Education Department
7128174
- AFL-CIO. American Federationist., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  November 1959.
  - Item 1: The American Federationist, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By The American Federationist. v.66:no.10 (1959:Nov.). Item is in English.
- A.F.L. American Federation of Teachers. Meet Workers Education Local 189., 1955; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Meet Workers Education Local 189., Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    By Local 189. Item is in English.
- American Labor Education Service. Labor Education Guide, 1956; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Labor Education Guide, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Orlie Pell. v.15:no.1 (1956:Spring/Summer). Item is in English.
- American Library Association. Public Libraries in the United States Today., 1954; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  October 1954.
  - Item 1: Bulletin. Public Libraries in the United States Today., Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    v.48:no.9 (1954:Oct.). Item is in English.
- American Management Association. Building Quality Into Manpower., 1948; Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  May 1948.
  - Item 1: Building Quality Into Manpower., Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Production Series Number 179. May 1948.. Item is in English.
- Banyai, Ed. Organizing the Unorganized., 1957; Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Training for Union Service talk by Ed Banyai, General Director of Organizing in Pennsylvania and Delaware, given to Officers' Qualification Courses Trade Union Techniques Class, December 4, 1957.
  - Item 1: Organizing the Unorganized., Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By Ed Banyai. Training for Union Service talk by Ed Banyai, General Director of Organizing in Pennsylvania and Delaware, given to Officers' Qualification Courses Trade Union Techniques Class, December 4, 1957. Item is in English.
- Carman, Harry J. The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and Workers' Education., 1926; Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Reprinted from Workers' Education, February 1926.
  - Item 1: The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and Workers' Education., Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By Harry J. Carman. Reprinted from Workers' Education, February 1926. Item is in English.
- Cohn, Fannia. Publications, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Can Women Lead?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, February 15, 1936. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Philosophy of Workers' Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Industrial and Labor Relations, v.1:no.4 (1948:July). 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: UNESCO: Its Objectives and How To Implement Them, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: Educational and Social Activities, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, Descember, 1929. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: I.L.G.W.U. Education Teaches Worker to Serve his Class, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. May 1, 1922. Photocopy. Item is in English.
  - Item 6: In Today's World: Cooperation = Security, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: The Uprising of the Sixty Thousand: The General Strike of the Dressmakers' Union, August 16, 1933., Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, September 1, 1933. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: Lest We Forget: the Nineteenth Anniversary of the Triangle Fire., Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, March 28, 1930. Item is in English.
  - Item 9: Our Education Department Goes Into Action, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, December, 1933. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 10: Working Women in Action, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers Education Bureau of America Quarterly, January, 1936. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 11: Workers' Education in War and Peace, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn; Spencer Miller, Jr.; Selig Perlman; Harry J. Carman. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 12: Wages Should Be Charged Against Industry: The Only Remedy Against Unemployment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, October, 1928. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 13: Why Workers' Education?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from the Souvenir Booklet of the Western Summer School for Workers. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 14: Method and Approach in a Discussion of the Economics of the Garment Industry for Young Workers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers Education Bureau of America Quarterly, March, 1937. Item is in English.
  - Item 15: Workers' Education in the World Crisis, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. May 21, 1940. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 16: Progressives Must Choose, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Woman-Today, People's Press, January, 1938. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 17: Workers' Education and the Social Studies, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Social Education, v.9:no.4 (1945:April). 2 copies. Item is in English.
- Cohn, Fannia. Speeches and articles., 1921-1949; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Teacher, Lecturer, Discussion Leader Gets His Inspiration From His Audience., Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Sew-Sew News, February. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: The Workers' University of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. From Life and Labor. No Date. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Workers' Education in War and Peace, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprint from The Workmen's Circle "Call". Item is in English.
  - Item 4: The Educational Work of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Report submitted to the Conference of the Workers' Education Bureau of America. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: Arthur Gleason: Interpreter of Workers' Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Spencer Miller, Jr. In Workers' Education. Item is in English.
  - Item 6: Arthur Gleason: Interpreter of the Workers' Mission, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. In Workers' Education. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: Arthur Gleason: A Champion of the Miners' Struggle, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By John Brophy. In Workers' Education. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: Brookwood Conference on Workers' Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Arthur Calhoun. In Workers' Education. Item is in English.
  - Item 9: Pioneer Youth of America, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, September, 1925. Item is in English.
  - Item 10: Copmany Unions and Workers' Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, October, 1926. Item is in English.
  - Item 11: Workers' Wives, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, November, 1926. Item is in English.
  - Item 12: Mothers and Children, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from the Lithographers' Journal, April, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 13: First Woman's Auxiliary Institute, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, January, 1928. Item is in English.
  - Item 14: The Adventures of Local 38, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 15: Labor's Voice on Unemployment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from The Womans Press, June, 1929. Item is in English.
  - Item 16: The Uprising of the Shirtwaist Makers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, November, 1929. Item is in English.
  - Item 17: Woman's Eternal Struggle, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Pioneer Woman, January, 1932. Item is in English.
  - Item 18: Social Responsibility, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from the Bulletin of the Taylor Society, June, 1933. Item is in English.
  - Item 19: A New Era Opens For Labor Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federaionist, February, 1934. Item is in English.
  - Item 20: Overheard, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. From Justice, February, 1934. Item is in English.
  - Item 21: Facing the Future, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. From Workers' Education, v.12:no.1 (1935:Jan.). Item is in English.
  - Item 22: Husbands and Wives, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, January, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 23: Are Women "Just Women"? Important Role of Union Auxiliaries, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, February, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 24: Are Women Organizable?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, March, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 25: Winning Workingwomen to Unionsim, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, April, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 26: Workingwomen and the Written Word, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, May, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 27: Challenge to Worker's Education, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. From Workers' Education, v.11:no.3 (1934:June). Item is in English.
  - Item 28: Workers' Education and Labor Leadership, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted for Workers Education Bureau of America. Item is in English.
  - Item 29: We Did Not Forget! A Worthy Memorial to the Triangle Victims, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from The New Leader, March 30, 1935. Item is in English.
  - Item 30: Triangle Memory Lives Again, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, April, 1934. Item is in English.
  - Item 31: Nutrition and Defense, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist. Item is in English.
  - Item 32: Meeting Our Problem, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers' Education Quarterly, January, 1935. Item is in English.
  - Item 33: How One Big Trade Union Has Dramatized Labor Problems, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers' Education News, May 18, 1935. Item is in English.
  - Item 34: Action Based on Knowledge is Power, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers Education Bureau of America Quarterly, July, 1936. Item is in English.
  - Item 35: The Workers Education Bureau: An Arm of the Labor Movement, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Workers' Education, October, 1936. Item is in English.
  - Item 36: History: Fiction or Fact, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Including Suggestions to all Teachers in Workers' Classes. Item is in English.
  - Item 37: All for One, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn; Irwin Swerdlow. One act play. Item is in English.
  - Item 38: Why Is Our Union Different?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Justice, September, 1939. Item is in English.
  - Item 39: Labor Unions and the Community, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 40: Understanding Basic Problems, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from American Federationist, November, 1949. Item is in English.
  - Item 41: Who Should Organize Women?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, June, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 42: Mrs. Martin Sees a Light, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, July, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 43: Lillian on the Sex Lines, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, August, 1927. Item is in English.
  - Item 44: Increased Productivity for Whom?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, April, 1928. Item is in English.
  - Item 45: Meeting the Machine's Challenge, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Fannia Cohn. Reprinted from Labor Age, May, 1928. Item is in English.
- Current History: The Monthly Magazine of World Affairs., 1954-1955; Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  July 1954. 3 copies. November 1955.
  - Item 1: Current History: The Monthly Magazine of World Affairs., Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    v.27:no.155 (1954:July) 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Current History: The Monthly Magazine of World Affairs., Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    v.29:no.171 (1955:Nov.). Item is in English.
- Digges, Dudley. Union Has its own College., 1956; Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
  March 1956.
  - Item 1: Union Has its own College., Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By Dudley Digges. Evening Sun, March 29, 1956. Photocopy. Item is in English.
- Dubinsky, David. Training for Union Leadership., Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 1: Training for Union Leadership., Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    By David Dubinsky. Reprint from USIS Feature. Item is in English.
- Gould, Ann. Settling Prices in Dresses., 1938; Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Training for Trade Union Service Course.
  - Item 1: Settling Prices in Dresses., Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    By Ann Gould. January 31, 1938. Training for Trade Union Service Course. Item is in English.
- Governors Conference: The Competent Consumer and How He gets That Way., 1955; Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
  May 1955.
  - Item 1: Governors Conference: The Competent Consumer and How He gets That Way., Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
    May 1955.. Item is in English.
- Gross, Murray. Function of the N.Y. Dress Joint Board Complaint Department., Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Trade Union Service Documents.
  - Item 1: Function of the N.Y. Dress Joint Board Complaint Department., Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By Murray Gross. Trade Union Service Documents. Item is in English.
- Hamburger, Siemon L. Background and Special Features of Trade Union Accounting., 1947; Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Training for Trade Union Service.
  - Item 1: Background and Special Features of Trade Union Accounting., Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
    By Siemon L. Hamburger. Training for Trade Union Service. From the Accounting Forum, December, 1946. Item is in English.
- Harvard Business School. Financial Reports of Labor Unions., 1950; Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Item 1: Financial Reports of Labor Unions., Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Abstract. Item is in English.
- Home Town Union: The Story of the I.L.G.W.U. in Fall River and Vicinity., 1948; Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Item 1: Home Town Union: The Story of the I.L.G.W.U. in Fall River and Vicinity., Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
    By District of Southern New England. Item is in English.
- Humphrey, Hubert H. Handling of Union Welfare Funds., 1954; Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Speech July 1954.
  - Item 1: Handling of Union Welfare Funds: Atricle by David Dubinsky., Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
    By Hubert H. Humphrey; David Dubinsky. Speech July 1954. Item is in English.
- I.L.G.W.U. Boston and District Educational Council. Halloween Ball. Souvenir Book., 1939; Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 1: Holloween Ball. Souvenir Book., Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
    By Boston and District Educational Council. Hotel Bradford, October 28, 1939. Item is in English.
- I.L.G.W.U. Educational Department. Arts in a Troubled World, 1947; Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
  May 1947. 2 copies; Part 1, 2 copies; Part 2, 2 copies.
  - Item 1: Arts in a Troubled World. Part 1., Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
    By Education Department. May 3, 1947. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Arts in a Troubled World. Part 2, Summary., Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
    By Henry David. May 3, 1947. 2 copies. Item is in English.
- I.L.G.W.U. Educational Department. At Your Service., 1946; Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Issues no.1-3 (1946: June-Dec.). 3 copies each no.1-2; 2 copies no.3. Brittle.
  - Item 1: At Your Service., Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
    By Education Department. Issues no.1-3 (1946: June-Dec.). 2 copies each. Brittle. Item is in English.
- I.L.G.W.U. Educational Department. Books for a Troubled World., 1946; Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
  March 1946. 3 copies.
  - Item 1: Books for a Troubled World: The Influence of Literature on Our Daily Life. The Contribution of Creative Criticism to the Enjoyment and Understanding of Good Books., Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By Fannia Cohn. March 2, 1946. Brown cover, 2 copies. Yellow cover, 1 copy. Item is in English.